Isabella Karle and Jerome Karle Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Isabella Karle and Jerome Karle Papers 1912-2010 1948-2008
MSS85507
Karle, Isabella, 1921-2017
Karle, Jerome
170,000 items
429 containers plus 65 oversize
200 linear feet
1,210 digital files (.93 GB)
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Physical chemists. Writings, speeches, correspondence, research data, subject files, photographs, notes, and miscellaneous textual materials in both physical and digital formats primarily relating to the Karles’ careers at the Naval Research Laboratory and their contributions to the field of crystallography.
Acquisition Information
The papers of Isabella Karle and Jerome Karle were transferred to the Library of Congress by the Naval Research Laboratory of the United States Navy in 2009. Additional items were transferred in 2010.
Transfers
Audiovisual materials have been transferred to the Motion Picture, Broadcasting, and Recorded Sound Division where they are identified as part of the Isabella Karle and Jerome Karle Papers. Patrons are encouraged to contact the Motion Picture, Broadcasting, and Recorded Sound Division in advance of a research visit.
Access and Restrictions
The Isabella Karle and Jerome Karle Papers are open to research. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting.
Technical Requirements
Digital files were created in a variety of operating systems. The content is primarily crystallographic data in .cif, .cw2, .cdx formats, text files in .doc, .txt, and .pdf formats, image files in .jpg and .tif formats, and presentations in .ppt format.
At the time of processing many of the files were inaccessible through available software. Many of these files contain crystallographic data created in programs from the 1980s to the early 2000s. As a result, these raw versions of the files do not appear as intended in their original hardware and software environments and often include altered formatting and extraneous characters. Files in .cdx format created in the program ChemDraw are not accessible.
One 8” floppy disk and thirteen computer tapes received with this collection are currently unprocessed due to lack of required hardware and not available for research.
Biographical Notes
Isabella Karle
Date Event
1921, Dec. 2 Born Isabella Helen Lugoski, Detroit, Mich.
1941 B.S., chemistry, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, Mich.
1942 M.S., physical chemistry, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, Mich. Married Jerome Karle (died 2013)
1944 Ph.D., physical chemistry, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, Mich. Research Associate, Manhattan Project, University of Chicago, Chicago, Ill.
1944 1946 Chemistry instructor, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, Mich.
1946 2009 Physicist, Naval Research Laboratory, Washington, D.C. (Head of Laboratory for the Structure of Matter X-Ray Analysis Section beginning in 1968)
1965 Awarded Navy Superior Civilian Service Award
1968 Awarded Society of Women Engineers Annual Achievement Award
1970 Awarded American Chemical Society Hillebrand Prize
1973 Awarded Federal Woman’s Award
1976 President, American Crystallographic Association Awarded American Chemical Society Garvan Medal
1978 Elected to National Academy of Sciences
1980 Awarded Captain Robert Dexter Conrad Award for Scientific Achievement, Office of Naval Research
1984 Awarded American Institute of Chemists Chemical Pioneer Award
1986 Awarded Women in Science and Engineering Lifetime Achievement Award (WISE)
1987 Awarded Secretary of the Navy Distinguished Achievement in Science Award
1988 Awarded Gregory Aminoff Prize, Royal Swedish Academy of Sciences Awarded Navy League Rear Admiral William S. Parsons Award
1991 Awarded National Institutes of Health Paul Ehrlich Prize
1992 Awarded American Peptide Society Vincent du Vigneaud Award Elected to American Philosophical Society
1993 Awarded the Franklin Institute Bower Award and Prize for Achievement in Science Elected to American Academy of Arts and Sciences
1995 Awarded National Medal of Science, Chemistry Awarded National Academy of Sciences Award in Chemical Sciences Awarded Department of Defense Distinguished Civilian Service Award
1997 Awarded American Chemical Society Ralph Hirschmann Award in Peptide Science
1998 Awarded Naval Research Laboratory Lifetime Achievement Award
2002 Awarded Office of Naval Research Fred E. Saalfeld Award for Lifetime Achievement in Science
2017, Oct. 3 Died, Arlington, Va.
Jerome Karle
Date Event
1918, June 18 Born Jerome Karfunkle, New York, N.Y.
1937 B.S., chemistry and biology, City College of New York, New York, N.Y.
1938 M.A., biology, Harvard University, Cambridge, Mass.
1938 1940 Laboratory technician, New York State Health Department, Albany, N.Y.
1942 Married Isabella Helen Lugoski (died 2017)
1943 1944 Technician, Manhattan Project, University of Chicago, Chicago, Ill.
1944 Ph.D., physical chemistry, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, Mich.
1944 1946 Laboratory technician, Naval Research Laboratory, Lubrication Section, Ann Arbor, Mich.
1946 1968 Supervisory physicist, Naval Research Laboratory, Washington, D.C.
1951 1970 Lecturer, University College of University of Maryland, College Park, Md.
1952 1955 Member, United States National Committee for Crystallography
1961 Elected fellow, American Physical Society
1967 1987 Member, National Academy of Sciences, National Research Council
1968 Appointed Chair of Science, Naval Research Laboratory Awarded Navy Distinguished Civilian Service Award
1968 2009 Chief scientist, Laboratory for the Structure of Matter, Naval Research Laboratory
1970 Awarded American Chemical Society Hillebrand Prize
1971 Vice president, American Crystallographic Association
1972 President, American Crystallographic Association
1973 1975 Chairman, United States National Committee for Crystallography
1974 1975 Chairman, National Research Council committee, “Status and Future Potential of Crystallography”
1976 Elected to National Academy of Sciences Awarded Captain Robert Dexter Conrad Award for Scientific Achievement, Office of Naval Research
1976 1977 Consultant, National Science Foundation
1979 1981 Member, Committee on Chemistry and Federal Policy, National Academy of Sciences
1981 1984 President, International Union of Crystallography
1984 Awarded American Crystallographic Association Patterson Award
1985 Awarded Nobel Prize in chemistry (with Herbert A. Hauptman)
1986 Awarded President’s Award for Distinguished Federal Civilian Service Awarded Secretary of Navy Award for Distinguished Achievement in Science Awarded Navy League Rear Admiral William S. Parsons Award Awarded National Library of Medicine medal
1988 1991 Chairman, Chemistry Section, National Academy of Sciences
1990 Elected member, American Philosophical Society
1993 Awarded Naval Research Laboratory Lifetime Achievement award
1994 Awarded 1992 Ettore Majorana-Erice “Science for Peace” Prize
2002 Awarded Office of Naval Research Fred E. Saalfeld Award for Lifetime Achievement in Science
2013, June 6 Died, Annandale, Va.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Isabella Karle and Jerome Karle span the years 1912-2012, with the bulk of the material dating from 1948 to 2008. The collection documents the Karles’ sixty-five year careers as physical chemists in the field of x-ray crystallography, most of which was spent at the Laboratory for the Structure of Matter at the Naval Research Laboratory (NRL) in Washington, DC. The papers are primarily in English, with Polish and some German, Russian, Spanish, and Chinese. The papers are organized into four series: Isabella Karle Papers, Jerome Karle Papers, Collaborations, and Oversize.
The collection focuses almost entirely on the Karles’ professional careers with little documentation of their personal lives. With the exception of the files in the Collaborations series, Isabella and Jerome maintained separate files which are arranged into distinct series, the Isabella Karle Papers and the Jerome Karle Papers. Both of their papers reflect the development and use of methods for crystal structure analysis with Jerome’s work skewing more toward theoretical investigations and Isabella’s work involving the development and execution of specific processes to analyze crystal structures, most of which were based on Jerome’s theories and calculations. Furthermore, Isabella’s papers focus mostly on her work within the laboratory, while Jerome’s reflect his wider involvement in the field as an administrator and participant in a variety of professional organizations and institutions. Though their working relationship is rarely evidenced in the files, it is explored through oral history interviews and other biographical materials throughout the collection. There is no documentation in the collection of their involvement with the Manhattan Project or other aspects of their career outside the NRL.
The Isabella Karle Papers series documents Karle’s scientific contributions to the field of x-ray crystallography and chiefly includes research and writing files produced at NRL, mostly between 1960 and 2008.
The Jerome Karle Papers document Karle’s contributions to the field of crystallography, his administrative career at NRL, and involvement in numerous scientific organizations, mostly between 1948 and 2008.
The Collaborations series contains materials related to projects, writings, speeches, and presentations on which Isabella and Jerome participated together, the bulk of which span from 1950 to 2009.
The remaining series contains Oversize files.
Arrangement of the Collection
This collection is arranged in four series:
Isabella Karle Papers, 1930-2010
Jerome Karle Papers, 1912-2009
Collaborations, 1920-2009
Oversize, 1958-2000
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Balaram, P., 1949-; Brenner, Steve, 1937-2020.; Hauptman, Herbert A. (Herbert Aaron), 1917-2011.; Huang, Lulu, (Scientist); Karle, Isabella, 1921-2017. Isabella Karle and Jerome Karle papers.; Karle, Jerome. Isabella Karle and Jerome Karle papers.; Massa, Lou.; Ranganathan, Darshan.; Ranganathan, Subramania.; Witkop, Bernhard, 1917-
Organizations
American Crystallographic Association.; American Philosophical Society.; International School of Crystallography.; International Union of Crystallography.; National Academy of Sciences (U.S.); National Institutes of Health (U.S.); NATO Advanced Study Institute.; Naval Research Laboratory (U.S.). Laboratory for the Structure of Matter.
Subjects
Chemistry, Physical and theoretical.; Chemistry.; Computational chemistry.; Crystallography--Computer programs.; Crystallography--Research.; Crystallography.; Crystals--Structure.; Electrons--Diffraction.; Molecular structure--Analysis.; Neutrons--Diffraction.; Oligopeptides.; Peptides.; Science and state--United States.; Science and state.; Women in chemistry.; Women in science.; X-ray crystallography--Research.; X-ray crystallography--Technique.; X-ray crystallography.; X-rays--Diffraction.
Occupations
Chemists.; Physical chemists.
Container List
- Isabella Karle Papers, 1930-2010 (Box 1-173)
  The Isabella Karle Papers series documents Karle’s scientific contributions to the field of x-ray crystallography and chiefly includes research and writing files produced at NRL, mostly between 1960 and 2008. Her papers include articles, correspondence, awards, performance appraisals, biographical sketches, oral history transcripts, professional membership files, and presentations given at scientific and academic conferences. The bulk of Isabella Karle’s series is represented by her Research File, which contains a significant volume of raw crystallographic data, notes, figures and illustrations of molecular structures, and correspondence with scientific collaborators at a variety of national and international institutions. Aside from a small number of biographical sketches and oral history transcripts, there are no files that document Karle’s childhood, personal and family life, education, or her work on the Manhattan Project.
  Arranged into five subseries.
  - Personal File, 1946-2008 (Box 1-6)
    The Personal File subseries contains materials that provide a broad overview of Isabella Karle’s career, mostly between 1970 and 2008. Files include awards and nominations, résumés, oral history transcripts, biographical sketches, and photographs. Of particular interest are Karle’s performance reviews and project reports from NRL that provide succinct overviews of her research, publications, speaking engagements, and other professional activities. Other materials document her involvement in various scientific societies including the National Academy of Sciences, the American Philosophical Society, and the American Crystallographic Association. Additional biographical materials related to Karle can be found in the Collaborations series and include awards, clippings, and oral history interviews.
    Material types include résumés, awards, certificates, oral history transcripts, biographical sketches, business cards, photographs, correspondence, memoranda, reports, applications, clippings, notes, calendars, and schedules. Some visual materials are in digital formats.
    Arranged alphabetically by subject or material type. The file structure of the digital content maintained as received.
    - Awards, 1961-2007, (6 folders) (Box 1)
    - Awards, 1961-2007, (3 folders) (Box 2)
    - Biographical sketches, 1965-2008 (Box 2)
    - Biographical sketches, 1965-2008, (2 folders) (Box 3)
    - Business cards, collected, 1997-circa 2008 (Box 3)
    - Calendars and schedules, 2006-2007 (Box 3)
    - Congratulations banner, 1980s (Box 3)
    - Curriculum vitae and résumés, circa 1962-1986, 2003 (Box 3)
    - Medical records, 1997-2002 (Box 3)
    - Naval Research Laboratory, Washington, DC (Box 3)
      - Application for employment, 1946 (Box 3)
      - Memoranda and administrative records, 1947-1979, 2001-2008 (Box 3)
      - Performance reviews, 1947-1979, (4 folders) (Box 3)
      - Performance reviews, 1980-2008, (4 folders) (Box 4)
      - Performance reviews, 2001-2006, mss85507_215_089; mss85507_215_090; mss85507_215_091
      - Project reports, 1973-1975 (Box 4)
      - Promotions and reassignments, 1947-1959, 1979-2008 (Box 4)
      - Senior Executive Service Women's Forum, 1990-1991 (Box 5)
    - Nominations for Nobel Prize, 1976-1985, (2 folders) (Box 5)
    - Oral history transcripts, 1993-2002, (2 folders) (Box 5)
    - Photographs (Box 5)
      - Equipment, 1950s-1960s (Box 5)
      - Portraits, 1949-1997 (Box 5)
    - Professional memberships, 1974-2006, (2 folders) (Box 6)
    - Publications citing Isabella Karle, 1957-2003, (2 folders) (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 1946-2009 (Box 6-17)
    The Correspondence subseries comprises professional correspondence received by Isabella Karle, mostly spanning from 1965 to 2000. The bulk of the subseries contains incoming letters from colleagues, publishers, and other scientists in her field. Topics documented include her research interests, status of projects and publications, involvement in professional organizations, arrangements for speaking engagements, biographical sketches, and referee comments by and for Karle. The subseries is not comprehensive, and most correspondence related to specific research, writings, speeches, and subjects can be found within files maintained according to topic throughout the series. Most letters addressed to both Isabella and Jerome can be found in the Collaborations series.
    Material types include letters, email printouts, memoranda, invitations, and attachments including writings, programs, and itineraries.
    Arranged alphabetically by subject, the bulk of which is a chronological file.
    - Chronological file, 1946-1959, (2 folders) (Box 6)
    - Chronological file, 1960-1973, (8 folders) (Box 7)
    - Chronological file, 1974-1980, (7 folders) (Box 8)
    - Chronological file, 1981-1987, (7 folders) (Box 9)
    - Chronological file, 1988-1992, (8 folders) (Box 10)
    - Chronological file, 1993-1998, (6 folders) (Box 11)
    - Chronological file, 1998-2003, (7 folders) (Box 12)
    - Chronological file, 2004-2009, (6 folders) (Box 13)
    - Reprint requests, 1951-1962 (Box 13)
    - Reprint requests, 1963-1973, (7 folders) (Box 14)
    - Reprint requests, 1974-1986, (6 folders) (Box 15)
    - Reprint requests, 1987-1996, (6 folders) (Box 16)
    - Reprint requests, 1997-1999, undated, (2 folders) (Box 17)
  - Speeches and Writings, 1944-2008 (Box 17-42)
    The Speeches and Writings subseries comprises files related to articles, reports, speeches, lectures, and book chapters written by Isabella Karle, mostly from 1960 to 2003. The files contain drafts, working files, figures, illustrations, research data, notes, abstracts, and correspondence. Frequent collaborators represented in the subseries include Darshan Ranganathan, Subramania Ranganathan, Padmanabhan Balaram, and Bernhard Witkop. The bulk of the speeches and writings correspond to the molecular structure analyses contained in Karle’s Research File. Published structures of these complex organic and inorganic substances include steroids, alkaloids, toxins, ionophores, and, especially, peptides, and relate to such varied topics as the transport of ions, protection against radiation damage, energetic and propellant materials, antimalarials, antibiotics, non-addicting analgesics, shock, neurotoxins, explosives, and nitrogen compounds. Also present in the subseries are Isabella’s lecture files from a variety of x-ray crystallography study institutes, many of which include lectures she presented with Jerome Karle. For additional materials from these study institutes, as well as writings and speeches written in collaboration with Jerome, see the Collaborations series. Additional writings, speeches, and related materials are interspersed throughout the Research File and Subject File.
    Material types include articles, notes, research, data, figures, illustrations, correspondence, conference programs, abstracts, speeches, travel files, photographs, and bibliographies. Some textual and visual materials are in digital formats.
    Arranged alphabetically by subject or material type and thereunder chronologically. The file structure of the digital content maintained as received.
    - Articles, 1944-1979, (6 folders) (Box 17)
    - Articles, 1980-1989, (7 folders) (Box 18)
    - Articles, 1988-1990, (5 folders) (Box 19)
    - Articles, 1989-1990, (6 folders) (Box 20)
    - Articles, 1990-1992, (5 folders) (Box 21)
    - Articles, 1990-1998, (5 folders) (Box 22)
    - Articles, 1992-1993, (6 folders) (Box 23)
    - Articles, 1992-1996, (6 folders) (Box 24)
    - Articles, 1994-1998, (7 folders) (Box 25)
    - Articles, 1996, mss85507_215_092
    - Articles, 1997-2002, (4 folders) (Box 26)
    - Articles, 2001, mss85507_215_093; mss85507_215_094
    - Articles, 2003-2008, (3 folders) (Box 27)
    - "Diffraction Studies of Model and Natural Helical Peptides," Membrane Protein Structure: Experimental Approaches, 1993 (Box 27)
    - Figures and illustrations, undated (Box 27)
    - Figures and illustrations, undated, (3 folders) (Box 28)
    - International Summer School on Crystallographic Computing, Prague, Czech Republic, 1975, July 28-Aug. 5 See also Container 416, same heading, (3 folders) (Box 28)
    - International Summer School on Supramolecular Chemistry, Strasbourg, France, 1990 (Box 29)
    - Lists of publications, 1963-2008 (Box 29)
    - Naval Research Laboratory release for publication requests, 1951-1953 (Box 29)
    - NATO Advanced Study Institute on Direct Methods in Crystallography, York, England, 1980, Aug. 4-15 See also Container 417, same heading, 1978-1980 (Box 29)
    - NATO Advanced Study Institute on Direct and Patterson Methods of Solving Crystal Structures, Parma, Italy, 1970, Sept. 7-19 See also Container 417, same heading (Box 29)
    - Referee and editor comments, 1951-1971, (3 folders) (Box 29)
    - Referee and editor comments, 1972-1987, (2 folders) (Box 30)
    - Reports, 1954-1955 (Box 30)
    - Review articles, 1977-1978 (Box 30)
    - Rontgenstrukturanalyse organisher Verbinungen, preface, 1972-1973 (Box 30)
    - Speeches, 1954-1969 (Box 30)
    - Speeches, circa 1965-1970s See also Container OV 2, same heading, (6 folders) (Box 31)
    - Speeches, 1975-1978, (5 folders) (Box 32)
    - Speeches, 1979-circa 1999, (4 folders) (Box 33)
    - Speeches, 1981-1984, (5 folders) (Box 34)
    - Speeches, 1984-1986, (5 folders) (Box 35)
    - Speeches, 1986-1988, (4 folders) (Box 36)
    - Speeches, 1988-1989, (4 folders) (Box 37)
    - Speeches, 1990-circa 1999, (4 folders) (Box 38)
    - Speeches, 1991-1993, (4 folders) (Box 39)
    - Speeches, 1994-1996, (4 folders) (Box 40)
    - Speeches, 1997-1999, (4 folders) (Box 41)
    - Speeches, 2000-2007, (4 folders) (Box 42)
  - Subject File, 1947-2010 (Box 42-55)
    The Subject File subseries comprises files from a variety of Karle’s professional efforts, and include name files, travel files, grant files, and slides. Name files contain correspondence, draft publications, notes, clippings, photographs, and crystallographic data related to specific projects undertaken by Karle and the identified individual. Travel files largely consist of Defense Department memoranda that detail Karle’s attendance at conferences, meetings, award ceremonies, and lecture engagements. Grant files include applications, progress reports, and correspondence related to the National Institutes of Health-funded “X-Ray Diffraction Studies of Oligopeptides” project from 1981 to 2008. The subseries also contains referee comments and recommendations by Karle. Of particular interest are the recommendations Karle wrote for her daughters Louise Karle Hanson and Jean Karle Dean, both of whom pursued careers in the field of chemistry. The associated correspondence in these files contains some of the only references in the collection to Jerome and Isabella Karle’s family life. Slides, arranged by subject, likely relate to speeches, lectures, and presentations though are not identified as such.
    Material types include correspondence, publications, notes, clippings, slides, photographs, research data, memoranda, applications, reports, letters of recommendation, and travel files. Some textual materials are in digital formats
    - Amines, Bernhard Witkop, slides, undated (Box 42)
    - Antam channel, slides, undated (Box 42)
    - BRITTS, CCD-dichloro/2,2 dichloro, slides, undated (Box 42)
    - Brossi, Arnold, 1990-1992 (Box 42)
    - C-tetrapeptides, slides, undated (Box 42)
    - Clippings, 1967, 1987-2002 (Box 42)
    - "Cohen reaction rate," slides, undated (Box 42)
    - "Combustion Dynamics Initiative," Department of Energy, 1991 (Box 42)
    - Conferences attended, 1962-1969, 1979-2004 (Box 42)
    - Daly, John W., 1971-2009 (Box 43)
    - "Eisner," slides, undated (Box 43)
    - Espelitia paper K-9, slides, undated (Box 43)
    - Frogs, slides, undated See also Container OV 2, same heading (Box 43)
    - Grochowski, Jacek, 1974-1980 (Box 43)
    - Hirschmann, Ralph Franz, 1992-2002, (3 folders) (Box 43)
    - L-pim, slides, undated (Box 43)
    - Li⁺ complex, slides, undated (Box 43)
    - Na antam, slides, undated (Box 43)
    - National Academy of Sciences, elections, 1978 (Box 43)
    - National Academy of Sciences, elections, 1979-1996, (11 folders) (Box 44)
    - National Academy of Sciences, elections, 1997-2004, (8 folders) (Box 45)
    - National Academy of Sciences, elections, 2006-2009, (3 folders) (Box 46)
    - "OBTUSA," slides, undated (Box 46)